<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl" ?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2021 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1"
	category="base"
	name="NXtransformations"
	type="group"
	extends="NXobject"
	ignoreExtraGroups="true"
	ignoreExtraFields="true"
	ignoreExtraAttributes="true"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd"
	>

	<doc>
		Collection of axis-based translations and rotations to describe a geometry.
		May also contain axes that do not move and therefore do not have a transformation
		type specified, but are useful in understanding coordinate frames within which
		transformations are done, or in documenting important directions, such as the
		direction of gravity.

		A nested sequence of transformations lists the translation and rotation steps
		needed to describe the position and orientation of any movable or fixed device.

		There will be one or more transformations (axes) defined by one or more fields
		for each transformation.  The all-caps name ``AXISNAME`` designates the
		particular axis generating a transformation (e.g. a rotation axis or a translation
		axis or a general axis).   The attribute ``units="NX_TRANSFORMATION"`` designates the
		units will be appropriate to the ``transformation_type`` attribute:

		* ``NX_LENGTH`` for ``translation``
		* ``NX_ANGLE`` for ``rotation``
		* ``NX_UNITLESS`` for axes for which no transformation type is specified

		This class will usually contain all axes of a sample stage or goniometer or
		a detector.  The NeXus default McSTAS coordinate frame is assumed, but additional
		useful coordinate axes may be defined by using axes for which no transformation
		type has been specified.

		The entry point (``depends_on``) will be outside of this class and point to a
		field in here. Following the chain may also require following ``depends_on``
		links to transformations outside, for example to a common base table.  If
		a relative path is given, it is relative to the group enclosing the ``depends_on``
		specification.

		For a chain of three transformations, where :math:`T_1` depends on :math:`T_2`
		and that in turn depends on :math:`T_3`, the final transformation :math:`T_f` is

		.. math:: T_f = T_3 T_2 T_1

		In explicit terms, the transformations are a subset of affine transformations
		expressed as 4x4 matrices that act on homogeneous coordinates, :math:`w=(x,y,z,1)^T`.

		For rotation and translation,

		.. math:: T_r &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} R &amp; o \\ 0_3 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix} \\ T_t &amp;= \begin{pmatrix} I_3  &amp; t + o \\ 0_3 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix}

		where :math:`R` is the usual 3x3 rotation matrix, :math:`o` is an offset vector,
		:math:`0_3` is a row of 3 zeros, :math:`I_3` is the 3x3 identity matrix and
		:math:`t` is the translation vector.

		:math:`o` is given by the ``offset`` attribute, :math:`t` is given by the ``vector``
		attribute multiplied by the field value, and :math:`R` is defined as a rotation
		about an axis in the direction of ``vector``, of angle of the field value.

		NOTE
		
		One possible use of ``NXtransformations`` is to define the motors and
		transformations for a diffractometer (goniometer).  Such use is mentioned
		in the ``NXinstrument`` base class.  Use one ``NXtransformations`` group 
		for each diffractometer and name the group appropriate to the device.
		Collecting the motors of a sample table or xyz-stage in an NXtransformation
		group is equally possible.
	</doc>
	<field name="AXISNAME" nameType="any" units="NX_TRANSFORMATION" type="NX_NUMBER" maxOccurs="unbounded">
		<doc>
			Units need to be appropriate for translation or rotation

			The name of this field is not forced.  The user is free to use any name
			that does not cause confusion.  When using more than one ``AXISNAME`` field,
			make sure that each field name is unique in the same group, as required
			by HDF5.

			The values given should be the start points of exposures for the corresponding
			frames.  The end points should be given in ``AXISNAME_end``.
		</doc>
		<attribute name="transformation_type" optional="true">
			<doc>
				The transformation_type may be ``translation``, in which case the
				values are linear displacements along the axis, ``rotation``,
				in which case the values are angular rotations around the axis.

				If this attribute is omitted, this is an axis for which there
				is no motion to be specifies, such as the direction of gravity,
				or the direction to the source, or a basis vector of a
				coordinate frame.
			</doc>
			<enumeration>
				<item value="translation" />
				<item value="rotation" />
				<!-- <item value="general" /> -->
			</enumeration>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="vector" optional="false" type="NX_NUMBER">
			<doc>
				Three values that define the axis for this transformation.
				The axis should be normalized to unit length, making it
				dimensionless.  For ``rotation`` axes, the direction should be
				chosen for a right-handed rotation with increasing angle.
				For ``translation`` axes the direction should be chosen for
				increasing displacement. For general axes, an appropriate direction
				should be chosen.
			</doc>
			<dimensions rank="1">
				<dim index="1" value="3" />
			</dimensions>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="offset" type="NX_NUMBER">
			<doc>
				A fixed offset applied before the transformation (three vector components).
				This is not intended to be a substitute for a fixed ``translation`` axis but, for example,
				as the mechanical offset from mounting the axis to its dependency.
			</doc>
			<dimensions rank="1">
				<dim index="1" value="3" />
			</dimensions>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="offset_units" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>
				Units of the offset.  Values should be consistent with NX_LENGTH.
			</doc>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>
				Points to the path to a field defining the axis on which this
				depends or the string ".".
			</doc>
		</attribute>
	</field>
	<field name="AXISNAME_end" units="NX_TRANSFORMATION" nameType="any" type="NX_NUMBER" minOccurs="0">
		<doc>
			``AXISNAME_end`` is a placeholder for a name constructed from the actual
			name of an axis to which ``_end`` has been appended.

			The values in this field are the end points of the motions that start
			at the corresponding positions given in the ``AXISNAME`` field.
		</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="AXISNAME_increment_set" units="NX_TRANSFORMATION"  nameType="any" type="NX_NUMBER" minOccurs="0">
		<doc>
			``AXISNAME_increment_set`` is a placeholder for a name constructed from the actual
			name of an axis to which ``_increment_set`` has been appended.

			The value of this optional field is the intended average range through which
			the corresponding axis moves during the exposure of a frame.  Ideally, the
			value of this field added to each value of ``AXISNAME`` would agree with the
			corresponding values of ``AXISNAME_end``, but there is a possibility of significant
			differences.  Use of ``AXISNAME_end`` is recommended.
		</doc>
	</field>
    <attribute name="default">
        <doc>
            .. index:: plotting
            
            Declares which child group contains a path leading 
            to a :ref:`NXdata` group.
            
            It is recommended (as of NIAC2014) to use this attribute
            to help define the path to the default dataset to be plotted.
            See https://www.nexusformat.org/2014_How_to_find_default_data.html
            for a summary of the discussion.
        </doc>
    </attribute>
</definition>
