<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl" ?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2008-2021 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd"
	name="NXcontainer"
	category="contributed"
	type="group"
	extends="NXobject"
	>

	<doc>
		State of a container holding the sample under investigation.
		
		A container is any object in the beam path which absorbs the beam and 
		whose contribution to the overall attenuation/scattering needs to be 
		determined to process the experimental data. Examples of containers 
		include glass capillary tubes, vanadium cans, windows in furnaces or 
		diamonds in a Diamond Anvil Cell. The following figures show a complex
		example of a container:
		
		.. figure:: container/ComplexExampleContainer.png
		   
		   A hypothetical capillary furnace. The beam passes from left to right
		   (blue dashes), passing through window 1, then window 2, before 
		   passing through the downstream wall of the capillary. It is then 
		   scattered by the sample with scattered beams passing through the 
		   upstream wall of the capillary, then windows 4 and 5. As part of the
		   corrections for a PDF experiment it is necessary to subtract the PDF
		   of the empty container (i.e. each of the windows and the capillary).
		   To calculate the PDF of the empty container it is necessary to have 
		   the measured scattering data and to know the nature (e.g. density, 
		   elemental composition, etc.) of the portion of the container which 
		   the beam passed through.
		   
		.. figure:: container/ComplexContainerBeampath.png
		   
		   A complete description of the shapes of the container elements with 
		   their orientation relative to the beam and also information on 
		   whether they are upstream or downstream of the sample is also 
		   therefore important. For example, although the windows 2 and 4 have 
		   the same shape, the path taken through them by the beam is very 
		   different and this needs to be modelled. Furthermore, it is not 
		   inconceivable that windows might move during an experiment and thus 
		   the changes to the beampath would need to be accounted for.
		
		This class encodes the position of the container with respect to the 
		sample and allows the calculation of the beampath through the container.
		It also includes sufficient data to model beam absorption of the 
		container and a link to a dataset containing a measurement of the 
		container with nothing inside, to allow data corrections (at a specific
		beam energy/measurement time) to be made.
	</doc>
	<field name="name">
		<doc>
			Descriptive name of container.
		</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="description">
		<doc>
			Verbose description of container and how it fits into the wider 
			experimental set up.
		</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="chemical_formula">
		<doc>
			Chemical composition of the material the container is made from.
			Specified using CIF conventions. Abbreviated version of CIF 
			standard: 
			
			* Only recognized element symbols may be used.
			* Each element symbol is followed by a 'count' number. A count of 
			  '1' may be omitted.
			* A space or parenthesis must separate each cluster of (element 
			  symbol + count).
			* Where a group of elements is enclosed in parentheses, the 
			  multiplier for the group must follow the closing parentheses. 
			  That is, all element and group multipliers are assumed to be 
			  printed as subscripted numbers.
			* Unless the elements are ordered in a manner that corresponds to 
			  their chemical structure, the order of the elements within any 
			  group or moiety depends on whether or not carbon is present.
			* If carbon is present, the order should be: 
			
			  - C, then H, then the other elements in alphabetical order of 
			    their symbol. 
			  - If carbon is not present, the elements are listed purely in 
			    alphabetic order of their symbol. 
			  
			* This is the *Hill* system used by Chemical Abstracts.
		</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="density" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_MASS_DENSITY">
		<doc>
			Density of the material the container is made from.
		</doc>
		<dimensions rank="1">
			<dim index="1" value="n_comp"/>
		</dimensions>
	</field>
	<field name="packing_fraction" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
		<doc>
			Fraction of the volume of the container occupied by the material 
			forming the container.
		</doc>
		<dimensions>
			<dim index="1" value="n_comp"/>
		</dimensions>
	</field>
	<field name="relative_molecular_mass" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_MASS">
		<doc>Relative molecular mass of container.</doc>
		<dimensions rank="1">
			<dim index="1" value="n_comp"/>
		</dimensions>
	</field>
	<group name="beam" type="NXbeam">
		<doc>
			Details of beam incident on container, including the position 
			relative to the sample (to determine whether the container is 
			upstream or downstream of the sample).
		</doc>
	</group>
	<group name="shape" type="NXshape">
		<doc>
			Shape of the container. In combination with orientation this 
			should allow the beampath through the container to be modelled to 
			allow the adsorption to be calculated.
		</doc>
	</group>
	<group name="orientation" type="NXtransformations">
		<doc>
			The angle the container makes to the beam and how it may change 
			during the experiment.In combination with shape this should allow 
			the beampath through the container to be modelled to allow the 
			adsorption of the container to be calculated.
		</doc>
	</group>
	<link name="reference_measurement" target="/NXentry">
		<doc>
			A link to a full data collection which contains the actual 
			measured data for this container within the experimental set up 
			(with no sample or inner container(s)). This data set will also 
			include the wavelength/energy, measurement time and intensity for 
			which these data are valid.
		</doc>
	</link>
</definition>

